Finding Aid for the Harold W. Fairbanks Papers LSC.0194
UCLA Library Special Collections
Harold W. Fairbanks papers
1894-1933
UCLA Library Special Collections
Fairbanks, Harold W. (Harold Wellman)
LSC.0194
4.0 Linear Feet (8 boxes and 2 shoeboxes)
Harold W. Fairbanks (b.1860) was an expert on the geology and geography of the Pacific Coast, and author of over 40 articles. His published works include Stories of our mother Earth (1899), Home geography (1902), Physiography of California (1903), and Stories of rocks and minerals (1903). The collection consists of manuscripts and published materials.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Helena Fairbanks, 1952
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942330033606533
We are committed to providing ethical, inclusive, and anti-racist description of the materials we steward, and to remediating existing description of our materials that contains language that may be offensive or cause harm. We invite you to submit feedback about how our collections are described, and how they could be described more accurately, by filling out the form located on our website: Report Potentially Offensive Description in Library Special Collections.
Biography
Fairbanks was born on August 29, 1860 in Conewango, New York; BS, University of Michigan, 1890; Ph.D, UC Berkeley, 1896; became an expert on the geology and geography of the Pacific Coast, and author of over 40 articles; published works include Stories of our mother Earth (1899), Home geography (1902), Physiography of California (1903), and Stories of rocks and minerals (1903).
Scope and Content
Collection consists of manuscripts and published materials.
Geologists -- California -- Archives.; Manuscripts for publication
- Writings: Geography in education, circa 1900 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
- Curriculum outlines: Geography in education, circa 1900 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
- Writings: Geography in education, circa 1900 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
- Notes: Geography in education, circa 1900 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Geographical Review, Published by the American Geographical Society of New York, October 1932 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Writings, circa 1900 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Writings: South American Geography, circa 1900 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Writings: Geography, circa 1900 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Writings: Geography in education, circa 1900 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Writings, circa 1900 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Writings and newspaper clippings, circa 1900 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Book manuscript: California geography, circa 1900 (Box 4, Folder 1-4)
- Writings, circa 1900 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Writings: The White Race in the Tropics, circa 1900 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Notes: Geography, circa 1900 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- UCLA Summer Session: California geography course, 1931-1933 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Writings, circa 1900 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Educational Publishing Company Agreement, 1902 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, circa 1900 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Harr Wagner Publishing Company: Correspondence, 1926-1929 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- World Book Company: Correspondence, circa 1900 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- University summer school class catalogs and commencement program, 1896-1933 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Material used by John Passerello for paper "Four Aspects of California Geography as Treated by Harold W. Fairbanks", circa 1900 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Notes and correspondence, circa 1900 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Newspaper clippings, circa 1900 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Book manuscript: The Natural Wealth of California, Its Origins and Car, circa 1900 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Writing and Notes: California geography, circa 1900 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Writing: California geography, circa 1900 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Offprints of periodical articles, circa 1900 (Box 7)
- Geography books, circa 1900 (Box 7, Box 8)
- Research citation index cards, circa 1900 (Box 9, Box 10)
  Scope and Content
  Contains research references filed under the following topics: California-General, Agriculture, Basin Province, Coast Range Province, Citites and Seaports, Climate, Communication, Earthquake Data, Fishing, Geology and Physiography, Great Valley, Historical, Mineral Wealth, Population, Sacramento Valley, San Joaquin Valley, Klamath Province, Sierra Nevada Province